Finding Aid for John H. Holland papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John H. Holland papers
1956-1982
Holland, John H. (John Henry), 1929-
4.50 linear feet
2010206 Aa 2
Professor of psychology, electrical engineering, and computer science at the University of Michigan beginning in 1959. Holland developed the concept of "genetic algorithms," research specializations in complex adaptive systems and artificial intelligence. First recipient of a computer science PhD at the University of Michigan, and a 1992 recipient of a MacArthur Fellowship. Papers consist primarily of departmental records pertaining to his professorial career, as well as research papers, notes, and correspondence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received from John Holland (donor no. 10391, in June 2010.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The John H. Holland papers are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The John H. Holland papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Box 5
John Henry Holland, a University of Michigan professor of psychology, electrical engineering, and computer science, helped pioneer the fields of artificial intelligence and the theory of complex adaptive systems. He is often called the father of genetic algorithms, having written a ground-breaking book on the subject in 1975 titled Adaptation in Natural and Artificial Systems.
Holland was born on February 2, 1929, in Fort Wayne, Indiana, and was raised in Ohio. He was educated at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, where he received a B.S. in physics in 1950, and the University of Michigan, where he received a M.A. in mathematics in 1954 and was the first recipient of a PhD in Computer Science at the University of Michigan in 1959. He joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1959, where he received the Louis E. Levy Medal of the Franklin Institute in 1961, as well as the UM Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award in 1987. A notable distinction in Holland's career was the bestowal of the prestigious MacArthur Foundation Fellowship in 1992, totaling $369,000 over a five year period.
In 1961 Holland became an assistant professor in communication sciences, and was promoted to professor in 1967. He became a professor of electrical engineering and computer science in 1984 when communication sciences became part of the College of Engineering. In 1988, he was named a professor of psychology, in addition to being appointed as professor of electrical engineering and computer science. Besides working at UM, Holland served as a consultant to the Los Alamos National Laboratory, and served as a member of the Board of Trustees and Science Board of the Santa Fe Institute. He was a research associate at the Carnegie Institution in Washington, D.C. and a consultant to Argonne National Laboratory, and was made a fellow of the World Economic Forum.
Holland's research expanded beyond computer science and mathematics, extending into the fields of psychology and communication sciences. He was a member of the pioneering group that programmed the earliest IBM computers in the 1950s, and studied how computers can evolve in noticeably human ways. His development of the concept of genetic algorithms was groundbreaking in the fields of computer science, communication science, psychology, and biology. These algorithms refer to a set of instructions that enable a computer to essentially learn, taking what it knows and making new rules, and adapting to new circumstances. Using computer models, Holland studied the process of adaptation in complex adaptive systems ranging from human organisms to the economy. These systems, he found, are constantly evolving, changing and interacting mechanisms that control everything from how people learn, to how advanced computers process information, to global economics and politics.
Holland is the author of a number of books, and has written and published countless articles and research papers.
The files are divided into six series: Correspondence, Departmental Records, Grants and Proposals, Presentations and Publications, Research, and Teaching.
The papers document the academic and professional aspects of John H. Holland's career as professor and researcher, from 1956-1982.
Subjects:
Artificial intelligence.; Computer science.; Computers--Study and teaching.; Holland, John H. (John Henry), 1929-2015.; Machine theory.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Computer and Communication Sciences.; University of Michigan. Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters, both incoming and outgoing, during the period from 1963 to 1978. These letters reflect John Holland's many research initiatives and intellectual collaboration with other academics and professionals, both nationally and internationally. They also document his various publications, projects, and presentations at conferences and panels, and are arranged in chronological order.
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation, Colleagues, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation, Students, 1969-1977 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2052 ]
- Departmental Records
  The Departmental Records series documents Holland's professorial and administrative career at the University of Michigan, spanning the years between 1961 and 1982. This is the largest series in the collection, and its records are organized thematically. The General Departmental records partly consist of memos within the Committee on the Degree Program in Communication Studies from 1961-1981, of which Holland was a member. They also contain information regarding program and course requirements, exam schedules, professorial appointments, and course structure.
  This series also contains documents regarding departmental budget, pertaining mostly to the School of Communication Sciences. These include memos, salary schedules, teaching load and corresponding budget information for Computer and Communication Sciences faculty members. Within this series is documentation of Holland's participation in the Center for Cognitive Science at the University of Chicago and the University of Michigan, from 1980 to 1982.
  Holland was a member of the Executive Committee and the Policy Committee for the Communication Studies Program, records from both of which are found in this series, dating from 1966 to 1981. These include memos, curriculum changes, Masters and PhD requirements, course and program evaluation reports, school statistics, and grading, admission, and advising guidelines.
  - General, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Center for Cognitive Science at University of Chicago & University of Michigan, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - General, 1963-1981 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Business/Early University Appointments, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee, 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - Policy Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
- Grants and Proposals
  Grants and Proposals is a series of records covering the period from 1956 to 1978 documenting the various grants and proposals with which Holland was involved. These include grants from NASA, The National Science Foundation and the EDG Advisory Group on Polymorphic Computers, and multiple proposals to the Office of Scientific Research.
  - Communication Sciences Center--Proposal and Correspondence, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Grant Applications, General, 1963-1971; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Initial drafts and original biographies for Office of Scientific Research Proposal, 1957 (Box 3)
  - NASA Grant [NSG 1176], "Comparative Analyses of Genetic Algorithms in Relation to Other Multimodal Function Optimization Techniques", 1973-1976; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - NSF Grant [GM 12236-09], "Computer Simulation in Biology: Theory and Practice", 1971-1978 (Box 3)
  - NSF Grant [MCS 76-04297], "Formal Theory of Multi-Dimensional, Nonlinear Systems, with Inter-Disciplinary Applications", 1971-1978 (Box 3)
  - Office of Scientific Research Proposal and Correspondence (1 copy of Logical Design Proposal), 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Office of Scientific Research Proposal, Masters, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - EDG Advisory Group on Polymorphic Computers, "A Proposal for the Investigation of Advanced Logical Design Methods for Computers Used in Large Scale Systems", 1960 (Box 3)
- Presentations and Publications
  The Presentations and Publications series consists of documents pertaining to Holland's attendance and/or presentations at various symposiums and conferences, as well as documents regarding his many published papers. The series includes invitations, publications, reprint requests, symposium and conference pamphlets, and correspondence between Holland and event organizers. The records are organized alphabetically.
  - Harvard Switching Theory Symposium, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Information Symposium and Proposal on Self-Organizing Work Leading to Office of Scientific Research Proposal, 1956 (Box 3)
  - IMMD Convocation (Institut Für Mathematische Maschinen und Datenverarbeitung), 1976 (Box 3)
  - Journal Association of Computing Machinery-"a logical theory...", 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - List of principle reports, papers, and publications of Logic of Computers Group, January 1964-June 30, 1965; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Masters/copy of 1956 Information Symposium paper (Box 3)
  - Memoranda on Artificial Intelligence; Inter-Disciplinary Seminar, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - New Zealand Embassy, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Original-Western Joint Computer Conference paper, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1958-1960; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Philosophy of Science Association Meeting, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Reprint requests for 1959 Eastern Joint Computer Conference paper, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Reprint requests for 1960 Western Joint Computer Conference paper, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Seminar at Blaricum, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
  - Western Joint Computer Conference, 1960 (Box 3)
- Research
  The Research series contains various papers by Holland, as well as reviews of colleagues' publications, personal research notes, and rough calculations. Notes on self-organizing models, the simplex method, and the distribution problem are included. The series extends from 1956 to 1962, and is arranged alphabetically.
  - Ashby's paper and review, "What is an Intelligent Machine?,", 1961 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1960-1962 (Box 4)
  - Central Nervous System Simulation/Research Computer, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Communication Science (Minutes, etc.), Before 1960; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Discussion of Burkes-Wane paper, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Distribution Problem (Linear Prog. Approach) (Box 4)
  - Institute of Science and Technology-Systems research, 1960-1962 (Box 4)
  - Rough calculations concerning Perceptron (Cornell Aerospace Lab) (Box 4)
  - Self-Organizing Models, 1956-1958 (Box 4)
  - Simplex Method (Box 4)
  - Student Programs and Summaries (prior to prelims), 1959-?; 4 folders (Box 4)
- Teaching
  The last series consists of Holland's Teaching records. These include course packs for various Computer and Communication Sciences courses, as well as notes, class material, and course evaluations. The series also contains documents pertaining to summer conference courses from 1960-1961. Included in the series as well are papers from doctoral committees on which Holland served, as well as PhD students' summary reports for which he sat on the examination panel. The entire series covers the period from 1963 to 1980, and is arranged chronologically. Some content in this series is restricted.
  - Course packs, CCS 805 (Computer and Communication Sciences), 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - CS 200 (Box 4)
  - CS 510 Signal Theory (Box 4)
  - CS 565 (Box 4)
  - CS 410 Communication Electronics, 1963 (Box 4)
  - CS 580, 1966 (Box 4)
  - CS 400 Introduction to the Communication Sciences, 1968 (Box 4)
  - CS 624 Theory of Adaptive Systems, 1968 (Box 4)
  - CS 805 Seminar in Adaptive Systems Theory, 1969-1980 (Box 4)
  - CS 422 Introduction to Artificial Intelligence, 1970 (Box 4)
  - CS 550, 1977-1980; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - CS 526, 1978-1980; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - CCS 385 LISP Mini-Course, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Course Evaluations CS 101 (Box 4)
  - Course Evaluations CS 550, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Summer Conference Course, 1960; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Summer Conference Course, 1961; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Doctoral Committees, 1963-1969 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary questions, undated (Box 4)
  - Summary Reports (John Holland was one of the panel members), 1974-1979; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Early Papers by CCS Students Later Recognized, 1966 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2041 ]
  - Student Records, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2037 ]
  - Student Records, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2038 ]
  - Student Records, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2039 ]
  - Student Records, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2040 ]
  - Student Records, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2042 ]
  - Student Records, 1968 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2043 ]
  - Student Records, 1969 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2044 ]
  - Student Records, 1974 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2049 ]
  - Student Records, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2051 ]
  - Student Records, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Student Records, 1978-79 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2054 ]
  - Student Records, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
    [SR Restricted until July 1, 2056 ]
  - Student Records, 1980-1981 (Box 5)